<resources>
    <string name="app_name">RoadTripHistory</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="section_format">Hello World from section: %1$d</string>

    <string name="Celilo_Desc">Celilo Falls (Wyam, meaning "echo of falling water" or "sound of water upon the rocks," in several native languages) was a tribal fishing area on the Columbia River, just east of the Cascade Mountains, on what is today the border between the U.S. states of Oregon and Washington. The name refers to a series of cascades and waterfalls on the river, as well as to the native settlements and trading villages that existed there in various configurations for 15,000 years. Celilo was the oldest continuously inhabited community on the North American continent until 1957, when the falls and nearby settlements were submerged by the construction of The Dalles Dam.[1]
For 15,000 years, native peoples gathered at Wyam to fish and exchange goods.[8] They built wooden platforms out over the water and caught salmon with dipnets and long spears on poles as the fish swam up through the rapids and jumped over the falls.[9] Historically, an estimated fifteen to twenty million salmon passed through the falls every year, making it one of the greatest fishing sites in North America.[10]
Celilo Falls and The Dalles were strategically located at the border between Chinookan and Sahaptian speaking peoples and served as the center of an extensive trading network across the Pacific Plateau.[11] Artifacts from the original village site at Celilo suggest that trade goods came from as far away as the Great Plains, Southwestern United States, and Alaska.[12] There are also numerous rock art drawings at the head of the falls. This demonstrates the site to not just be important for trading purposes. It acted as a melting pot for the cultures which fished and traded there.[13] When the Lewis and Clark expedition passed through the area in 1805, the explorers found a "great emporium…where all the neighboring nations assemble," and a population density unlike anything they had seen on their journey.[14] Accordingly, historians have likened the Celilo area to the “Wall Street of the West."[15] The Wishram people lived on the north bank, while the Wasco lived on the south bank, with the most intense bargaining occurring at the Wishram village of Nix-luidix.[11] Charles Wilkes reported finding three major native fishing sites on the lower Columbia — Celilo Falls, the Big Dalles, and Cascades Rapids, with the Big Dalles being the largest. Alexander Ross described it as the "great rendezvous" of native traders, as "the great emporium or mart of the Columbia."[2] Pinnipedssuch as sea lions and seals followed salmon up the Columbia as far as Celilo Falls. In 1841 George Simpson wrote "these animals ascend the Columbia in great numbers in quest of the salmon.[16]
As more settlers arrived in the Pacific Northwest in the 1930s and 1940s, civic leaders advocated a system of hydroelectric dams on the Columbia River. They argued that the dams would improve navigation for barge traffic from interior regions to the ocean; provide a reliable source of irrigation for agricultural production; provide electricity for the World War II defense industry; and alleviate the flooding of downriver cities, as occurred in the 1948 destruction of Vanport City, Oregon. Aluminum production, shipbuilding, and nuclear production at the Hanford site contributed to a rapid increase in regional demand for electricity. By 1943, fully 96 percent of Columbia River electricity was being used for war manufacturing.[21] The volume of water at Celilo Falls made The Dalles an attractive site for a new dam in the eyes of the Corps of Engineers. Throughout this period, native people continued to fish at Celilo, under the provisions of the 1855 Treaties signed with the Yakama Nation,[22] the Confederated Tribes of Warm Springs,[23] and the Walla Walla, Umatilla, and Cayuse,[24] which guaranteed the tribes\' ancient "right of taking fish at all usual and accustomed stations." In 1947, thefederal government convened Congressional hearings and concluded that the proposed dam at The Dalles would not violate tribal fishing rights under the treaties.[25]Subsequently, the government reached a monetary settlement with the affected tribes, paying $26.8 million for the loss of Celilo and other fishing sites on the Columbia.[26] The Army Corps of Engineers commenced work on The Dalles Dam in 1952 and completed it five years later. On March 10, 1957, hundreds of observers looked on as a rising Lake Celilo rapidly silenced the falls, submerged fishing platforms, and consumed the village of Celilo, ending an age-old existence for those who lived there. A small Native American community exists today at nearby Celilo Village, on a bluff overlooking the former location of the falls.
In 2008 the Army Corps of Engineers completed a survey of the Celilo Falls site using sonar technology, in response to the 50th anniversary of the flooding of the falls. The survey revealed that the falls remain intact below the artificial lake, and that "rocky outcrops, carved basins and channels that match aerial photographs from the 1940s."[27] Legacy[edit]
Celilo Falls retains great cultural significance for native peoples. Ted Strong of the Intertribal Fish Commission told one historian, "If you are an Indian person and you think, you can still see all the characteristics of that waterfall. If you listen, you can still hear its roar. If you inhale, the fragrances of mist and fish and water come back again."[25] In 2007, three thousand people gathered at Celilo Village to commemorate the 50-year anniversary of the inundation of the falls.[28]
</string>

    <string name="Starvation_Desc">About ten miles east of the town of Cascade Locks runs a stream that goes by the name of Starvation Creek. On December 19 a blizzard left massive snowdrifts across the newly completed tracks of the Oregon Railway Navigation Company and the snowstorm trapped the pacific Express, the overland limited between St. Paul, Minnesota and Portland. The train made an unscheduled stop and almost immediately snow covered the engine and much of the rest of the train. It was impossible to return to Hood River only ten miles back much less continue fifty miles ahead to Portland where many of the 148 passengers expected to spend their Christmas holidays. The conductor rummaged through the train an located three cases of oysters, two quarters of beef, some mutton, and about seventy-five jackrabbits.
Initial efforts to dig out the train failed, but during a lull in the storm, crewmen succeeded in backing the cars a few hundred feet onto a small wooden trestle where they hoped passengers were out of danger from avalanches. As the storm increased, blowing and drifting snow prevented plows from reaching the stranded train from either The Dalles or Portland. On December 22 a dwindling food supply forced the conductor to send every able-bodied man out into the blizzard, each to seek his own safety. All survived the arduous trek to Troutdale, where rescuers from nearby Portland met them. Men on skis managed to pull heavy sleds of food to feed the remaining passengers.
Christmas came and went. Holiday dinner consisted of bacon, beans, canned fruit, pickles, and coffee. Rescue efforts continued around the clock, but progress was agonizingly slow. Drifts topped fifty feet in places, and snow mixed with iced forced solid wall across the tracks between Multnomah Falls and Oneonta Gorge. Plows derailed and a locomotive tipped over, fatally crushing an engineer. An army of a thousand men recruited from Portland used picks and shovels to dig away at snow and ice walls. New Year’s Day passed, but the train remained snowbound until the weather abruptly warmed a few days later. Shortly after midnight on the morning of January 8, the remaining passengers finally steamed into Portland. They arrived almost three weeks late.
</string>

    <string name="Oregon_Desc">Among early business enterprises in Oregon, the Oregon Steam Navigation Company (OSN) stands out as uncommon on two counts. Quite against the dominant trend in the Pacific Northwest, OSN was funded by local investors who were determined to keepPortland’s interests uppermost. In addition, OSN effectively operated for two decades with a near monopoly over steam-powered water transportation on the Columbia River, from the lower river to interior locations as far from Portland as present-day Lewiston and Lake Pend Oreille, Idaho. OSN was extremely unpopular because of its tough-minded business practices and its stranglehold on shipping.
In 1850, steamboat transportation came to the Oregon Country, first in regular connections between Astoria and Portland on the Columbia, a shallow-draft sidewheeler, and then on a sizable boat built at Milwaukie on the Willamette River, the Lot Whitcomb. By the mid 1850s, steamboats operated on the Willamette above the falls to Dayton, on the Yamhill River, and on the Columbia from Astoria to the interior. The traffic on the Columbia was broken up into three segments: the lower river from Astoria to the Cascades; the middle river from the Cascades to The Dalles; and the upper river from above Celilo Falls to landings nearly 250 miles from Portland
Steamboat owners on the lower river—John Ainsworth, Benjamin Stark, William S. Ladd, and Jacob Kamm—sought an integration of Columbia River transportation to take advantage of increasing traffic to mining fields in the interior. The capitalists purchased The Dalles-Celilo portage and the Colonel Wright from Thompson and also gained control of the Cascades portages from the owners—William and Putnam Bradford on the Washington side and Harrison Olmstead and Joseph Ruckel on the Oregon side—who retained their property rights in the portages and received royalties as compensation. The new company, OSN, filed corporate papers in Washington Territory in 1860 and in Oregon in 1862. The first corporate board members included Ainsworth, Ladd, Kamm, Ruckel, Bradford, Lawrence Coe representing Thompson’s interests, and Simeon Reed on behalf of Benjamin Stark.
OSN brought the company’s investors nearly a 50 percent return on their money in 1862. Within two years, its boats had carried nearly 100,000 passengers and 60,000 tons of freight upriver from Celilo. The OSN’s elegant Carrie Ladd, a sternwheeler with well-appointed cabins, ran the lower river to the Cascades; the Idaho, a sidewheeler, steamed up to The Dalles; and the Colonel Wright worked the upper river. The company also built new boats and expanded service to Arrow Lake in British Columbia and on Lake Pend Oreille to connect with Montana mining districts.
By 1864, the company had purchased the portages from Bradford and Ruckel and two portage railroads on the north and south banks of the river. The Oregon portage railroad included use of the state’s first steam railroad engine, the Oregon Pony. In the late 1860s, OSN operated eighteen boats on the Columbia and Snake Rivers and had a commanding presence in The Dalles, where it constructed an enormous warehouse, tool shops, a hotel, and a sizable wharf.
Although OSN was successful and ambitious, factions developed among the company’s thirty-three stockholders. In 1866, divisions widened over OSN’s decision to build theOregonian, a 270-foot steamer, to compete against Ben Holladay’s Pacific Mail Steamship Company for ocean-going ship traffic between
San Francisco and Portland. Daniel Bradford led discontented owners in criticizing OSN’s expansion and chastising company managers for a decrease in earnings in 1866 and 1867.
By the end of 1867, disgruntled stockholders had sold out, leaving OSN with just seven owners. Company directors Ainsworth, Reed, Ladd, and Thompson ran the company and quickly bought up remaining shares, before increasing capitalization in 1868by selling new shares to railroad financier Jay Cooke and the Northern Pacific Railroad. OSN’s fate became entwined with the Northern Pacific’s financial woes during the 1870s. By 1879, Henry Villard, the representative of German bondholders with a huge stake in the Northern Pacific, had arranged purchase of OSN from Ainsworth. The company disappeared into the apparatus and finances of a transcontinental railroad.
The Oregon Steam Navigation Company was a colossus during its brief existence. Its ambitious directors constructed an effective transportation network that included four railroads—the Walla Walla and Columbia River Railroad, the Dalles Portage Railroad, and two railroads at the Cascades portage. When the Northern Pacific absorbed the company, OSN handed over twenty-six steamboats; hundreds of acres of real estate in Portland, Astoria, The Dalles, Umatilla, and Vancouver; and more than $3 million in equipage.
</string>
</resources>
